Where's my jumper from? Er, it's Gucc— No, it's my grandma's. I think she knitted it.
我的毛衣是哪来的？呃，是古驰……不，是我奶奶的。我觉得是她织的。
I look really wholesome.
看起来特别淳朴、健康、很有亲和力。
And the fact it was from my grandma, it's like a hug, innit.
而且这是我奶奶送的，就像一个拥抱一样，不是吗？
My name is Will Gao. I'm an actor and a musician.
我叫Will Gao。我是一名演员，也是一名音乐人。
This chair's wonky.
这把椅子有点歪歪扭扭的。
As you can see, we're in a forest.
如你所见，我们现在在一片森林里。
Jessie is, like, three years old. Jessie
大概三岁左右。
I give her, like, cheeky bits of cheese.
我会偷偷喂她一点点奶酪。
I want to be her favorite.
我想成为她最喜欢的人。
I don't know many different types of cheeses, but Cheddar, yeah?
我不太懂各种奶酪，不过切达奶酪我还是知道的。
Maybe if she's lucky, Camembert.
要是她运气好的话，还能吃到卡芒贝尔奶酪。
What's the squi— That's the squidgy one, isn't it?
那个软软的是叫什么来着？就是那个软乎乎的那个，对吧？
Yeah. This is her main stomping ground.
对。这就是她最常活动的地盘。
We're in Croydon right now. My stomping ground as well.
我们现在在Croydon。这也是我从小活动的地方。
My mum's Chinese, and my dad's English, and we grew up kind of in both cultures, in Chinese culture and also English culture.
我妈妈是中国人，爸爸是英国人，所以我们是在两种文化中长大的，既有中国文化，也有英国文化。
I was the oldest child with my little sister, who I'm also in a band with and I work with very closely, and then my little brother as well.
我是家里的老大，下面有一个妹妹，我和她还组了乐队，也经常一起工作，还有一个弟弟。
So, my dad's English, and he doesn't speak any Chinese.
我爸爸是英国人，他一点中文都不会说。
He doesn't really speak— Yeah, he tried, but it didn't work out.
他其实不会说……嗯，他试过学，但最后没成功。
But my mum's Chinese, and she kind of grew up speaking to me in Chinese, so I kind of have a vocabulary.
不过我妈妈是中国人，她从小就用中文和我说话，所以我还是有一些中文词汇量的。
Mostly when she was angry at me.
主要是在她生我气的时候。
Like, when she's getting annoyed, it'll be in Chinese, so I know a lot of, like, rude and naughty words in Chinese.
比如她开始不耐烦的时候，就会切换成中文，所以我学会了很多中文里的脏话和调皮话。
Bèn dàn. It means "silly egg." "
笨蛋"。字面意思就是"傻鸡蛋"。
My mum used to call me a bèn dàn a lot at the time.
我妈妈那时候经常叫我"笨蛋"。
I went to an all-boys school throughout my whole education, and I just didn't feel, like, this sense of belonging that a lot of my friends felt.
我整个学生时代都在男校读书，但我一直没有那种很多朋友都有的归属感。
And I think that was, like, a really big part of my childhood.
我觉得那是我童年非常重要的一部分。
But now it's great because I'm in a place where I get to explore that a lot, and I really get to, like, dissect why that is and why I was feeling like that.
但现在很好，因为我到了能够深入探索这些问题的阶段，也终于能够认真剖析为什么会这样，以及当时为什么会有那样的感受。
It actually clicked when I saw a play in London called The Great Wave.
直到我在伦敦看了一部叫《The Great Wave》的话剧，我才一下子明白过来。
It was at the National Theatre, and it was an all East Asian cast.
那是在国家剧院演出的，而且演员全部都是东亚裔。
And I had this overwhelming sense of inclusivity, and I got to meet a couple of the actors afterwards.
当时我感受到一种特别强烈的包容感，后来还有机会见到了几位演员。
It was pretty cool.
真的特别棒。
I feel the pressure of being one of few British East Asian actors who are leading the industry, I guess, or being the most visible, so I feel that need to be able to speak about this issue and to be really honest about it.
作为少数活跃在行业前列、曝光度最高的英籍东亚裔演员之一，我确实感到一种压力。所以我觉得自己有责任去谈论这个议题，并且真诚地表达自己的想法。
I didn't feel represented on screen.
我觉得自己没有在荧幕上得到代表。
On television, especially in the UK, we have such an issue with representation.
在电视上，尤其是在英国，族群代表性一直是一个很大的问题。
Only now I'm starting to see East Asian … British East Asian actors being represented in acting and in our industry in general.
直到现在，我才开始看到东亚裔，尤其是英籍东亚裔演员，在影视行业以及整个行业中逐渐得到更多的呈现。
I think it's been really recent, and we've got a long way to go, but we're nowhere near where we need to get … so yeah.
我觉得这一切其实都是最近才开始的，我们还有很长的路要走，而且距离真正理想的状态还差得很远。
My dad was an actor, a true theater actor, and a lot of his friends are in that kind of creative world and space.
我爸爸是一名演员，一位真正的戏剧演员，他的很多朋友也都在创意行业工作。
And I think I looked up to my mum and dad's love of culture and art, and I think that really influenced me growing up, and I think a couple of teachers at school as well.
我很敬佩我父母对文化和艺术的热爱，我觉得这对我的成长影响很大，学校里的几位老师也是如此。
I think music and the world of theater and performance are very linked together.
我觉得音乐、戏剧和表演其实是紧密联系在一起的。
My school was connected with a commercial boys choir, and so I spent four years doing a lot of opera, which is a really niche thing.
我的学校和一个职业男童合唱团有合作，所以我花了四年时间演歌剧。歌剧其实是一个挺小众的领域。
But I learned a lot more about music, and also it gave me a great opportunity to practice acting because opera's very … very dramatic and intense.
不过我学到了很多音乐知识，而且歌剧也给了我很多练习表演的机会，因为歌剧本身就非常戏剧化、情绪浓烈。
Beijing opera, like, the "Ba!", like, that stuff, yeah, that's … that's really intense.
京剧，比如那种"吧！"的唱腔，就是那种感觉，真的特别有张力。
I went to one in Beijing. It's, like, one hour of organized carnage.
我在北京看过一场。感觉就像一个小时的"有组织的混乱"。
I remember performing in a Shakespeare opera, A Midsummer Night's Dream by Benjamin Britten, and I was playing one of the fairies.
我记得我演过一部根据莎士比亚作品改编的歌剧《仲夏夜之梦》，作曲是Benjamin Britten，我演的是其中一个小仙子。
So I spent a few years doing that, and then my voice broke.
所以我唱了几年歌剧，后来变声了。
I got fired.
结果我被"开除了"。
But I still enjoy music, and I still enjoyed acting, but I was forced to go back to school, which was shit.
不过我还是喜欢音乐，也喜欢表演，只是不得不回学校读书，那真的很糟糕。
My mum always said, like, "Just keep at it."
我妈妈总是说："坚持下去。"
My mum was like, "Just keep going because at some point you'll be able to … come back."
我妈妈总是说："继续坚持，总有一天你会回过头来看这一切。"
"And realize that the hard work paid off," you know. "
到时候你就会发现，所有的努力都是值得的。"
Yeah. My mum and my dad, they cared a lot about my education and, like, what I was up to.
是啊，我爸妈一直很重视我的教育，也很关心我每天在做些什么。
But then when I was like, "You know what?" "Actually, I want to be an actor. I want to be a musician." "I want to be creative," they were pretty supportive of it, actually.
但后来当我说："你知道吗？其实我想当演员，我想做音乐，我想从事创意工作。"他们其实都非常支持我。
I was blessed in that respect.
在那方面，我真的很幸运。
The scariest moment of my life? You're just rushed out, and suddenly there's a camera, like, "boomph," and I forgot my line completely.
你就这样被匆忙推了出去，突然镜头"唰"地对着你，我一下子把台词全忘了。我人生中最可怕的一刻？
You've got a lot of people around. Got used to it, though.
周围围着很多人。不过后来也就习惯了。
Two months after Heartstopper came out, I was walking down the street, and there's a group of young girls, and one of them, like, broke down crying, like, kind of seeing me, and then—I think they'd just seen the show.
Heartstopper播出两个月后，我走在街上，看到一群年轻女孩，其中一个看到我之后突然哭了出来。我猜她们刚刚看完那部剧。
It had such a profound impact on so many people, and it really helped people discover themselves and realize that they had a place and a group that they were accepted into.
它对很多人都产生了深远的影响，也帮助很多人认识了真正的自己，并意识到自己也有一个可以被接纳、属于自己的群体。
I think the great thing about having an ensemble cast and a cast of, I mean, we're all the same age, right?
我觉得群像演员阵容最大的好处就是，我们年龄都差不多。
We're all between the ages of, like, 17 and 22, 23, so we're all there to support each other, and I think it was such a huge moment for all of us.
我们都在17岁到22、23岁之间，所以大家都会互相支持。我觉得那对我们所有人来说都是人生中的一个重大时刻。
I remember giving many a call to some of my castmates to check in with them, see if they were OK.
我记得我给很多一起演戏的演员打电话，关心他们，看看他们是否还好。
Life just turned up a notch, like, the noise of life, and also the accelerator pedal was like "vrooooph."
生活一下子升级了一个档次。生活的噪音变大了，人生的油门也一下踩到底了。
Sebastian Croft, I had a long-ass streak with him that ended when I deleted Snapchat.
我和Sebastian Croft原本保持了超长的Snapchat连续打卡记录，但我删掉Snapchat之后就断了。
I learned a lot about the history of the LGBT community.
我学到了很多关于LGBT群体历史的知识。
I explored Stonewall and gay rights movement and how little there actually has been.
我去了解了Stonewall事件、同性恋权益运动，也意识到其实真正取得的进步还很有限。
And it was really empowering to be part of that show because, like, this show is, like, the first show that's really celebrating it and not just using it as some, like, negative spin-off.
能参与这部剧真的让我很有力量，因为它是真正去庆祝这个群体，而不是把它当作一个负面的附属元素来消费。
I did a bit of modeling for a bit.
我以前也做过一段时间模特。
I was, like, in East Croydon Station, as you do.
当时我就在East Croydon车站，很平常嘛。
And this lady came up to me, and she was like … "Well, what's your name?"
有位女士走过来问我："你叫什么名字？"
I was like, "Will," and she kind of scouted me.
我说"Will"，然后她就把我发掘了。
I thought it was, like, a scam, but it turned out it was legit.
我一开始还以为是骗局，结果竟然是真的。
I had some crazy stories from it, like fashion show afterparties are … they're nuts.
我经历了很多疯狂的事情，比如时装秀的庆功派对，真的太疯狂了。
Underage. Shh.
那时候我还没到法定年龄。嘘。
I've gone to Beijing quite a few times in my life because my grandparents are there, and a lot of my family are there.
我人生中去过北京很多次，因为我的祖父母和很多家人都在那里。
Seeing my grandma LaoLao in the outskirts of Beijing and just stay there with her.
去北京郊区看我的外婆"姥姥"，然后陪她住一段时间。
She cooked many a meal.
她给我做了无数顿饭。
Beijing to London, I'd love to bring those stalls with, like, hot peanuts and, like, snacks and traditional Chinese pancakes.
如果是从北京带到伦敦，我最想把那些卖热花生、小吃和中式煎饼的小摊一起搬过去。
I think it's the breakfast food there, like bao buns and, like, baozi.
我最怀念的是北京的早餐，比如包子之类的。
I remember every time we'd get there, like, in the morning, my grandmother would prepare them, like, fresh from the market.
我记得每次早上到北京，我外婆都会用刚从市场买回来的新鲜食材给我们准备早餐。
I think Croydon could do with some of those.
我觉得Croydon也很需要这些东西。
Chinese food is just the vibe.
中餐真的就是最对味、最有感觉。
My dad's knowledge of cooking, like, he had, like, one recipe book.
我爸爸对做饭的了解基本就来自一本菜谱。
He had a Delia Smith cookbook, and he followed that like religion.
他有一本Delia Smith的菜谱，而且完全照着做，简直奉若圣经。
Whereas my mum kind of improvised, and she had that training from … passed down from, like, grandparents, great-grandparents.
而我妈妈更多是凭经验发挥，因为她的厨艺是一代代从祖辈那里传承下来的。
I can't handle spicy food. I literally can't handle it.
我真的吃不了辣，一点都不行。
I'm a … I'm a shame to my mum.
我真是给我妈妈丢脸了。
Introducing— Oh, my sister's not here. Me and Olivia, who's my wonderful and very talented sister, started a band called Wasia Project in 2018.
下面介绍……噢，我妹妹不在。 我和我特别优秀、非常有才华的妹妹Olivia在2018年组建了一个叫Wasia Project的乐队。
But then it kind of started to build, and we started doing shows, and we released an EP that did really well.
后来乐队慢慢有了起色，我们开始演出，还发行了一张成绩很不错的EP。
And then we've kind of been thrown into this kind of chaos of releasing music and being in the studio and going to gigs, and it's been really, really fun.
后来我们就一下子投入到发歌、录音、跑演出这样忙碌又混乱的生活中，不过真的特别开心。
Most songs now, we both do together.
现在大多数歌曲都是我们俩一起完成的。
Like, I'll bring an idea, she'll develop it, we'll sit in a room, talk about it, and then when we produce it, obviously, we're there together … arguing, but healthy, healthy arguing.
比如，我先提出一个想法，她会把它进一步完善，我们会坐在一个房间里讨论它，然后制作的时候，我们当然也会一直待在一起……争论，不过是那种健康的、建设性的争论。
Also, songwriting's such a vulnerable thing.
而且，写歌本身就是一件非常需要袒露内心的事情。
I think, especially at times where I've been quite low or written songs that are quite sad, and vice versa for her, we've been uncomfortable to share it, but we know exactly what the vibe is.
尤其是在我情绪低落、或者写了一些很悲伤的歌的时候，她也是一样，我们都会有点不好意思分享，但彼此都能立刻明白那种感觉。
Like, we'll turn, face away from each other, and, like, it's really sweet.
比如，我们会转过身，背对着彼此，那画面还挺温馨的。
ABBA and Queen and, like, The Beatles were, like, an underscore for my whole childhood. ABBA、Queen
和 The Beatles 的音乐几乎成了我整个童年的背景音乐。
And me and my sister, there's so many home movies of just us, like, dancing to, like, ABBA and just hearing these sounds that made me want to move and perform.
我和我妹妹有很多家庭录像，里面都是我们跟着 ABBA 跳舞，听着那些音乐，那些声音让我忍不住想动起来、想表演。
I think my dad played more ABBA, and he played The Beatles, a lot of The Beatles, and Frank Sinatra.
我爸爸更多放的是 ABBA，还有 The Beatles，尤其是很多 Beatles 的歌，以及 Frank Sinatra。
And then my mum played, like, a lot of Bee Gees, a lot of Carpenters, and they're a big influence now for me and my sister because, obviously, the Carpenters were siblings as well.
而我妈妈则经常放 Bee Gees 和 Carpenters。现在他们对我和我妹妹影响都很大，因为 Carpenters 本身也是兄妹组合。
It's such a privilege to say that I literally get to make music with my sister for a living.
能够说自己靠和妹妹一起做音乐谋生，这真的是一种幸运。
It's just mad.
这真的太疯狂了。
I think I'm quite a frantic person, especially before gigs.
我觉得自己是个挺容易慌乱的人，尤其是在演出前。
I'm quite nervous, and I'm high energy and frantic, and she's really chilled.
我会特别紧张，精力旺盛又有点慌，而她就特别放松。
She's collected, and she's calm, and it's like yin and yang.
她很沉着、很冷静，我们俩就像阴和阳一样互补。
The idea comes from scratch when you're writing a song.
写歌的时候，一个想法往往是从零开始产生的。
It comes from nothing, or it comes from an emotion, feeling, like sadness or happiness or love or friendship, and you attach them.
它可能源于一无所有，也可能源于某种情绪，比如悲伤、快乐、爱情或友情，然后你把这些情感串联起来。
It's such a raw kind of craft.
这是一门非常原始、非常真实的创作艺术。
Whereas with acting, I think you're bringing … you're finding the emotion within a piece of writing.
而演戏则不同，你是在一段已经写好的文本中去寻找情感。
That's the biggest difference.
这就是两者最大的区别。
There are challenges, like, everywhere you go.
无论走到哪里都会遇到挑战。
But for me, with acting and music, believing in myself was a big thing.
但对我来说，无论是演戏还是做音乐，真正重要的是相信自己。
Yeah. Mitski is an artist that is just …so interesting in just everything she's been doing.
嗯，Mitski 是一位非常有意思的艺术家，她做的每一件事都特别吸引我。
Dream collab would be with Mitski.
我最梦想合作的对象是 Mitski。
So if Mitski's seeing this, please.
所以如果 Mitski 看到了这个，请联系我吧。
I saw her live at the Roundhouse, and she is just insane.
我在 Roundhouse 看过她的现场演出，她真的太厉害了。
Just the whole soundworld she's created is like … just such a fusion.
她创造出来的整个音乐世界，就是一种非常奇妙的融合。
It's like … it's a love letter to, like, 1980s Japan, but it's also just through, like, the lens of modern-day pop, which is just so inspiring for me and Olivia.
它就像是一封写给 20 世纪 80 年代日本的情书，但又是通过现代流行音乐的视角来呈现，这对我和 Olivia 来说特别有启发。
I just kind of try and stay disconnected from social media.
我尽量让自己远离社交媒体。
I try and stay in real life as I possibly can.
我尽可能多地活在现实生活里。
But TikTok is becoming a very broad platform now, and I think it's not just TikTok dances.
不过现在 TikTok 已经变成了一个内容非常丰富的平台，不再只是跳舞视频了。
There's so many people doing so many different things.
有很多人在上面做着各种各样的内容。
So I actually think I need to embrace TikTok more than I have been.
所以我觉得自己应该比现在更积极地接受、使用 TikTok。
Not doing TikTok dances because that would be very embarrassing, and I wouldn't want to do that.
不过不会去跳 TikTok 舞，因为那对我来说太尴尬了，我可不想这么做。
My dancing will never be seen.
我的舞姿永远不会公开。
Like, yeah, that's not— That … that can't happen.
对，那可不行，绝对不能发生。
No one can see my— Yeah, no.
谁都不能看到我的……算了，不行。
I think I'm going to stick with the music and the acting as the main … as the main thing.
我觉得我还是会把音乐和演戏作为自己的主业。
I want to, like, fuse my two kind of worlds into one and explore, like, projects that incorporate both.
我希望把我的两个世界融合在一起，去尝试那些能够同时结合音乐和表演的项目。
Jessie was born … three years ago. She was a tiny puppy.
Jessie是三年前出生的。 那时候她还是一只很小的小狗。
And we called her Jessie because I think … I can't remember.
我们给她取名 Jessie，不过为什么叫这个名字，我已经记不清了。
And then I just remember walking her lots and caring for her.
我只记得经常带她出去遛，还一直照顾她。
Yeah, I really like Jessie, but she does literally the stinkiest poos, like, it's actually—
我真的很喜欢 Jessie，不过她拉的便便真的臭到离谱。
You saw today, the poos, like, it was literally abysmal.
你今天看到她拉的便便了吧，真的臭得惨不忍睹。
I hope this doesn't make the final cut.
希望这一段不会被剪进最终版本。